Ann Nolan Clark papers, 1962-1979
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Ann Nolan Clark papers, 1962-1979
MS 309
Clark, Ann Nolan, 1898-
Manuscripts, correspondence, talks, and miscellaneous personal material. Bulk of collection is handwritten and typed drafts of ten of Clark's books published between 1965 and 1979. Material for A Child's Story of New Mexico contains only correspondence with the publishers and revisions. Most manuscripts represent several versions of a story. Other materials include a photograph of Clark, typescripts and an audiotape of talks and speeches, and a few letters to Clark chiefly from her publisher.
1.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Born in Las Vegas, New Mexico on December 5, 1896, Ann Nolan grew up with children of diverse backgrounds. She graduated from New Mexico's Highlands University in 1919 with a degree in Education. In 1920, she married Thomas Patrick Clark and they had one son.
While Clark worked as a teacher for the U.S. Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1920-1962, she began writing books for children that reflected their culture. She also worked for the Institute of Inter-American Affairs in Central and South America, 1945-1950, training teachers and writing materials for the classroom. Her work with various cultures was a source for her children's books.
She was awarded the New York Herald Tribune Spring Festival Award for In My Mother's House, 1941, and Looking for Something, 1942; the Newbery Medal, 1952, for Secret of the Andes; U.S. government's Distinguished Service Award, 1962; and the Regina medal, 1963. Throughout her career, her writings, including over 28 trade titles, have presented a variety of cultures with dignity and respect. She died in Tucson on December 6, 1995.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
I. Personal Materials, 1962-1978
II. Manuscripts, 1965-1979
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of this collection consists of drafts of ten of Clark's books published after 1965. Material for A Child's Story of New Mexico consists of correspondence with the publisher about revisions for the 1969 edition.
The manuscripts often represent several versions of the stories and most contain numerous edits by Clark. The sequence of drafts is often unclear. The draft entitled "Tam and Cam", published as In the Land of Small Dragon, is a Vietnamese folk tale told to Clark by Dang Manh Kha.
Also present are supplemental items such as an 8x10 black-and-white photograph of Clark by Laura Gilpin; a summary of her royalty earnings from April 30, 1968; her bibliography; a list of children's authors in Tucson, Arizona and their books from the 1960s; a typescript of a 1962 talk given to the Texas Association of School Libraries; an audiotape "Writing for and with children"; and a few letters to Clark.
Access Terms
Clark, Ann Nolan, 1898- -- Archives
Children's literature -- Manuscripts
Manuscripts -- American
Manuscripts
Container List
- Series I: Personal Materials, 1962-1978
  - Miscellaneous personal materials. Includes 1962 talk, "Writing for and with children," given to an audience of teachers of young children, Tucson, Arizona. 1962-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Manuscripts, 1965-1979
  - A Child's Story of New Mexico (correspondence and revisions only). 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A White Cloth for the Table. No Date (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - All this Wild Land. One draft with corrections. 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arizona for Young People. One bound draft. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Circle of Seasons. Two drafts with corrections. 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Hoofprint on the Wind. One draft. 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Journey to the People. Three drafts with corrections. A compilation of earlier lectures. 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Read All About It. One draft. No Date (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Summer is for Growing. Three drafts with corrections. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Tam and Cam (published as In the Land of Small Dragon: A Vietnamese Folktale). Four drafts and one letter to the publisher. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - The Wind Blows Strong (published as To Stand Against the Wind). Four drafts with corrections. 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3-7)
  - To Stand Against the Wind. Master proof with author's changes. 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)